狮子是王权的象征
Lions are the very image of majesty.
也是非洲的形象代表
And, indeed, of Africa itself.
它们的力量来自于狮群的强大
Their strength lies in the power of the pride,
紧密团结的家族
their tight-knit family.
狮子已统治大草原数千年
Lions have ruled the savannahs for millennia.
然而  最近二十年左右
And yet, within the last 20 years or so,
它们的数量减少了将近一半
their numbers have fallen by almost half.
我们的团队用了两年时间
Our team has spent two years following
追踪肯尼亚马赛马拉的玛莎狮群
perhaps the most famous lion family of all,
这也许是最有名的狮子家族
the Marsh pride of Kenya's Masai Mara.
我们加入时  这个伟大王朝的生存
As we join them, the very survival of this great dynasty
已危在旦夕
is under threat.
它们的未来完全依仗于
Their future depends entirely
一位超凡领袖的
on the strength and determination
力量与决心
of one extraordinary leader.
它也许是玛莎狮群历史上
Perhaps the most powerful in the history
最为强大的首领
of the Marsh pride.
这头母狮名叫沙尔姆
A lioness known as Charm.
狮子
马赛马拉
The Masai Mara.
狮群在这里蓬勃繁衍
The pride have always thrived here
靠的是强壮的首领公狮
through an alliance between powerful alpha males
保护家族
to protect the family
经验丰富的母狮抚育幼崽
and experienced females to raise the cubs.
然而  玛莎狮群史上首次
But, for the first time in the pride's history,
这种狮群成员间的合作破裂
this alliance has been shattered.
所有的成年公狮抛弃了家族
The family has been abandoned by all the adult males.
狮群的存亡落在了沙尔姆
The survival of the pride now rests upon the shoulders of Charm
还有它的同族姐妹西恩娜肩上
and her cousin, Sienna.
仅剩的两头成年狮子
The only remaining adults.
若希望幼狮长大成年
If their young are to reach adulthood
王朝重回鼎盛
and the dynasty return to full strength,
它们必须担起保护与喂养全家的双重责任
they must now both protect and feed the whole family.
八月
August.
几场雨后  食物充裕的时期到来
Following the recent rains, it's a time of plenty.
狮子周围到处都是牛羚
The lions are surrounded by wildebeest
它们正在年度迁徙途中
on their annual migration.
一头二百五十千克的公牛可以让
A quarter-tonne bull would make a good meal
狮群的十头狮子饱餐一顿
for all ten of the pride.
但尽管沙尔姆是一位经验丰富的猎手
But even though Charm is an experienced hunter,
多数尝试都以失败告终
most attempts end in failure.
沙尔姆用后腿蹬踹  使牛羚失去平衡
Charm uses her hind legs to knock the wildebeest off-balance.
最小的幼崽在未来的十二个月内
The smallest cubs won't be able to catch food for themselves
尚无能力自己捕食
for another 12 months.
它们的胃口渐长  意味着沙尔姆和西恩娜
Their ever-growing appetites mean that Charm and Sienna
必须夜以继日地捕猎
have to hunt around the clock.
母狮经常被迫独自出行
The females are often forced to head out alone.
今晚  轮到西恩娜捕猎
Tonight, it's Sienna's turn.
日出时分
Sunrise.
西恩娜身受重伤
Sienna is seriously injured.
它虚弱到无法移动
She's too week to move.
一头落单的狮子很容易受到野牛
A lone lion is always at risk of attack by buffalo,
鬣狗  甚至其它狮群的攻击
hyenas, even other lion prides.
日落时分
It's evening,
西恩娜仍然没有回到家人身边
and Sienna hasn't returned to her family.
如今  一切都要靠沙尔姆了
Now, everything depends on Charm.
夜幕降临
As night falls,
沙尔姆别无选择  只能独自出发捕猎
Charm has no choice but to head out to hunt,
留下脆弱的幼崽
leaving the vulnerable cubs alone.
它被尾随了
She's being trailed.
是鬣狗
Hyenas.
一旦得到机会  它们会攻击落单的狮子
They'll attack lone lions if they get the chance,
将它们的猎物占为己有
to steal any kill they make.
沙尔姆必须在被它们找到之前快速动手
Charm must work fast before they find her.
它们追踪到了它
They've tracked her down.
仅靠自己  它无法抵御它们
On her own, she couldn't hold them off.
不过  狮群的另一位成员一直跟着沙尔姆
But another of the pride has been following Charm.
它三岁的女儿  雅雅
Her three-year-old daughter, Yaya.
狮群的其它成员赶到
The rest of the pride arrive.
来进食
To eat.
雅雅挺身而出保护狮群
Yaya has stepped up to help defend the pride
并供养家族
and feed her family.
女儿终生留在母亲身边
Daughters stay with their mothers for life,
最终也许会有自己的幼崽
and may eventually have cubs of their own.
雅雅还未成年  但作为沙尔姆的大女儿
Yaya is not yet an adult, but as Charm's eldest daughter,
它是狮群首领的继任者
she's next in line to lead the pride.
沙尔姆还有一个三岁的儿子  塔图
Charm also has a three-year-old son, Tatu.
开始长出引人瞩目的鬃毛
The beginnings of an impressive mane are a sign
是它接近成年的标志
of his approaching adulthood.
像每个青少年一样
Like every adolescent,
塔图一有机会
Tatu can't resist the chance
就想测试自己日渐增长的力量
to test his growing strength.
甚至去挑衅一头两吨重的河马
Even against a two-tonne hippo.
不过它并非狮群中唯一的年轻雄狮
But he's not the only young male in this pride.
它的同族兄弟  雷德
His cousin, Red.
过去几个月间  它们之间
Over the last few months, the two of them have begun
开始建立同盟
to forge an alliance.
但即使一起行动  它们还是奈何不了
But even together, they're not really going to worry
一头发怒的河马
an angry hippo.
和姐妹们不同  儿子长大后
Unlike their sisters, sons always leave their family
总是会离开家族
when they reach adulthood.
它们之间渐强的情感纽带
Their growing bond
或许能让它们强强联手  结伴离开
may enable them to leave as a powerful partnership.
最终  它们会与其它公狮作战
Eventually, they'll fight other males
尝试统领自己的狮群
to try and take over a pride of their own.
但是眼下  它们仍然需要
But for the time being, they still need Charm
沙尔姆的照顾
to look after them.
距西恩娜被攻击已过去四天
It's been four days since Sienna was attacked.
它爬起身来
She's back on her feet.
但它急需进食
But she's in urgent need of a meal.
它实在没有足够的力气
She simply doesn't have the strength.
随着它们逐渐成熟  年轻的公狮
As they mature, young males begin to
开始探索狮群领地的边界
explore the boundaries of the pride's territory.
雷德独自出来探险
Red has ventured out alone.
它冒失地闯入一群鬣狗之中
And blundered straight into the middle of the hyena clan.
它被二十多条鬣狗困住了
He's trapped by over 20 of them.
鬣狗群试图拖垮它
The pack tries to wear him down.
这么多鬣狗足以杀死它
This number of hyenas could kill him.
同时对抗所有的鬣狗根本不可能
It's impossible to fight them all at once.
它无法跟它们对峙太久
He can't keep them at bay for much longer.
它在迅速衰弱
He's tiring fast.
它的盟友塔图听到骚动
His ally, Tatu, has heard the commotion.
现在局势逆转
Now, the odds have changed.
即使是二十条鬣狗
Even for 20 hyenas,
也无法对抗两头公狮
a pair of male lions is too much to take on.
雷德很幸运
Red is lucky.
塔图救了同族兄弟的命
Tatu has saved his cousin's life.
数周来西恩娜靠零碎食物果腹
After weeks of feeding on scraps,
现在它终于有力气去与家族重聚
Sienna has grown strong enough to try and rejoin her family.
它先向沙尔姆问候
She greets Charm first.
即使分开这么久
Even after being apart for so long,
它们之间的情感纽带依然坚固
the bond between them is still strong.
雅雅也欢迎西恩娜重回狮群
Yaya also welcomes Sienna back into the pride.
沙尔姆的家族终于团圆
At last, Charm's family are back together.
沙尔姆不但重获捕猎伙伴
Charm not only has her hunting partner back,
另一位猎手也成长起来
but another hunter is emerging.
雅雅正逐渐长成一头强壮的母狮
Yaya is becoming a powerful lioness.
它已学会如何潜行
She's learned how to stalk.
身体放低
Stay low.
悄无声息地
Approach silently.
逆风接近
And from downwind.
但是成功伏击的关键是不被发现
But the key to a successful ambush is not being noticed.
一旦被发现
Now it's seen her,
头顶尖角的牛羚更占上风
the wildebeest, with its sharp horns, has the advantage.
不过雅雅在学习中进步
But Yaya is learning.
母女之间逐渐建立伙伴关系
Mother and daughter are starting to develop their partnership.
时值十月
It's October.
牛羚的大迁徙永不停歇
The great wildebeest migration never stops.
现在它们要离开马赛马拉
And now, they're leaving the Masai Mara.
对沙尔姆和它的家族来说
For Charm and her family,
获取食物将变得更加困难
food is about to become much more difficult to find.
草原现在空空荡荡
The plains are now empty.
为了寻找食物
And, in search of food,
沙尔姆带领狮群来到领地的边缘
Charm leads the pride to the edge of their range.
它在这里找到另一种猎物
Here, she finds another kind of prey.
被非法带入狮群领地放牧的牛
Cattle, illegally brought into the lions' territory to graze.
猎牛是喂饱它饥饿家族的机会
An opportunity to feed her hungry family.
但也可能招致灾难
But hunting cattle can lead to disaster.
为了保护牲畜
To protect their livestock,
牧民有时会布设毒饵
herdsmen sometimes put out poisoned bait.
狮子无法判断食物是否有毒
Lions can't tell when a meal is toxic.
一周后
A week later,
沙尔姆一岁的儿子  已经病得爬不起来
Charm's one-year-old son is so ill he can hardly stand.
整个狮群都显现出中毒症状
The whole pride are showing the signs of poisoning.
而西恩娜再次失踪了
And Sienna is missing once again.
随着温度的上升  狮群出发寻找阴凉处
As the temperature climbs, the pride heads off to find shade.
但是痛苦的幼狮虚弱得无法跟上
But the struggling cub is too weak to follow.
沙尔姆需要和狮群待在一起
Charm needs to stay with the rest of the pride.
几小时后  幼狮还是没有追上妈妈
Hours later, the cub still hasn't caught up with his mother.
而西恩娜也不见踪影
And there's no sign of Sienna, either.
第二天  沙尔姆回到儿子身边
The next day, Charm returns to her son's side.
它仍然步履蹒跚
He's still very unsteady.
但是它的妈妈不能弃狮群于不顾
But his mother can't abandon the rest of the pride.
为了狮群  沙尔姆抛弃它的幼子
For the sake of the pride, charm abandons her young cub.
其它狮群成员在等它
The others are waiting for her.
它们前所未有地需要它
They need her now more than ever.
它再也不会见到活着的儿子
She will never see her son, or Sienna,
或是西恩娜
alive again.
尽管失去亲人  沙尔姆和它的王朝
Despite her losses, there may still be a future
仍有未来的希望
for Charm and her dynasty.
它最大的孩子  雅雅和塔图
Her eldest cubs, Yaya and Tatu,
从中毒中幸存下来
have survived the poisoning.
沙尔姆带领狮群不断迁移  寻找猎物
Charm keeps the pride moving in a constant search for prey.
即使有雅雅的帮助
Catching enough food is hard,
捕获足够的猎物仍然很难
even with Yaya's help.
但沙尔姆绝不放弃
But Charm is relentless.
狮群里的年轻成员也努力向它学习
The younger members of the pride try to follow her example.
虽然猎物稀少  鬣狗又不断骚扰
Even with little to hunt and the constant harassment of hyenas,
沙尔姆作为领袖的技能和经验
Charm's skill and experience as a leader
让狮群得以存活
is keeping the pride alive.
几周后  它的努力开始收到回报
A few weeks later, her efforts begin to be rewarded.
塔图和雷德已经超过四岁
Tatu and Red are now over four years old,
准备好迈出成年的最后一步
ready to take the final step to adulthood.
它们该离开狮群了
It's time for them to leave the pride.
对沙尔姆来说  这就是成功
For Charm, this is success.
它们结伴离开  并肩与其它公狮作战
They head out as a partnership, to battle other males,
争取属于自己的狮群
to win a pride of their own,
并在别处延续家族血脉
and continue the family's bloodline elsewhere.
但是沙尔姆仍需照顾剩下的四头母狮
But Charm still needs to get the remaining four female cubs
安全长至成年
safely to adulthood.
五月的一个清晨
One early morning in May...
成年公狮的吼叫
..The roar of adult male lions.
两头外来的新公狮
Two new males, outsiders,
在寻找可以统领的狮群
are searching for a pride to take over as their own.
新的公狮可以带来养育
New males could bring the possibility
新一代幼崽的可能性
of a new generation of cubs.
但它们也同样可以轻易带来灾难
But they could just as easily bring disaster.
不久  新的公狮开始
Soon, the new males begin to impose their authority
向玛莎狮群施加压力
on the Marsh pride.
沙尔姆的小女儿还没到繁殖年龄
Charm's youngest daughter is still too young to breed.
对于雄狮来说  它只不过是又一只
To the males, she's nothing more than another mouth
分享食物的同类
to share food with.
它们不想让它留在自己的狮群
They don't want her in their pride.
沙尔姆尽可能地努力保护女儿
Try as she might, Charm struggles to defend her daughter.
即使它也无法与成年雄狮相匹敌
Even she is no match for an adult male.
沙尔姆试着分散它们的注意
Charm tries distracting them,
用自己的身体挡在幼崽前
putting herself between them and her cub.
但是这没有用
But it's no good.
如果它女儿留下  最终会死于雄狮口下
If her daughter stays, the males will eventually kill her.
幼狮除了离开别无选择
The cub has no choice but to leave.
雄狮并不满足于此
And the males don't stop there.
所有幼狮都被驱逐
Every young cub is driven out.
它们前途未卜
Their future is uncertain.
沙尔姆对此无能为力
There's nothing Charm can do.
八个月前
Eight months ago,
沙尔姆的狮群有十头狮子
Charm's pride numbered ten lions.
现在只剩下它和雅雅
Of them, only she and Yaya now remain.
最终  角马群的回归标志着艰难时期
The return of the wildebeest signals the end, at last,
终于结束
of the hard times.
是时候重新开始了
Time for a new beginning.
沙尔姆正开始
Charm is starting the process
重建玛莎狮群
of rebuilding the Marsh pride.
它和一只雄狮远离了
She and one of the males have separated themselves
狮群其它成员
from the rest of the group.
雌狮每过几个月
Females are only able to conceive
才能受孕一次
once every few months.
在那些重要的日子  雄狮会一直在它身边
For those crucial days, the male won't leave her side.
沙尔姆离雄狮很近
Charm stays close to him
以稳固它们的感情纽带
to strengthen their bond.
如果雄狮无法确定未来的幼崽是它的孩子
If the male isn't certain any future cubs are his,
它可能会杀死它们
he will probably kill them.
四个月过去了
Four months later.
沙尔姆远离狮群  独自生活
Charm is alone, away from the pride.
在过去的十四个月中
Over the last 14 months,
它的王朝面临毁灭
her dynasty has faced ruin.
但现在  新的希望诞生
But now, there is new hope.
只有两周大
Just two weeks old.
沙尔姆远离狮群生下幼崽
Charm gave birth away from the others.
过分好奇而笨手笨脚的狮子
Inquisitive and clumsy lions
对新生幼崽可能造成威胁
could be a threat to the newborns.
但沙尔姆的两只幼崽依然极度脆弱
But her two cubs are still extremely vulnerable.
水牛群搜寻狮子幼崽
Buffaloes seek out lion cubs
有机会时会杀死它们
and will kill them if they get the chance.
沙尔姆用身体护卫着幼崽
She shields them with her body.
没有它的保护
Without her to protect them,
水牛会把幼崽们踩死
the buffalo will trample them to death.
沙尔姆迫使整个水牛群打退堂鼓
Charm has forced the entire herd to back down.
对于狮子幼崽  危险无处不在
Life is always dangerous for lion cubs.
但这两只幼崽
But these two
有一位经验丰富的母亲照顾它们
have an experienced mother to look after them.
最终  沙尔姆的狮群得以再次壮大
At last, Charm's pride is increasing again.
一只雄狮和一只雌狮
One male and one female.
这些幼崽也许很快就会有新的伙伴
And these cubs may soon be joined by more.
雅雅和另一只成年雄狮组成配对
Yaya has paired off with the other adult male.
很快  它也会有孩子
Soon, she too will have cubs.
沙尔姆的孙辈
Charm's grandchildren.
沙尔姆正第一次带它的幼崽
Charm is taking her cubs to meet
去见玛莎狮群的其它成员
the rest of the Marsh pride for the first time.
它们的父亲一旦接受幼崽
Once their father has accepted the cubs,
就会像它们的母亲一样拼命保护它们
he'll defend them as fiercely as their mother.
它们也代表着它的王朝的未来
They are the future of his dynasty, too.
沙尔姆自从生产就远离狮群
Charm has been away from the pride since giving birth,
已有几周没见过雅雅
and hasn't seen Yaya for weeks.
它们之间的纽带撑过了这个狮群
Their bond has held through perhaps the hardest times
史上最艰难的时光
in the pride's history.
它的女儿也已孕育幼崽
With her daughter pregnant
它的儿子亦踏上寻找自己狮群之路
and her son looking for a pride of his own,
沙尔姆的王朝和玛莎狮群
Charm's dynasty and the Marsh pride
得以存续
will live on.
这头非凡的雌狮获得了成功
This extraordinary lioness has succeeded.